<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xml:lang="en-GB"><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="4.4.1">Jekyll</generator><link href="https://vikv.dev/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" /><link href="https://vikv.dev/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" hreflang="en-GB" /><updated>2025-07-13T21:59:09+01:00</updated><id>https://vikv.dev/feed.xml</id><title type="html">Alembic</title><subtitle>Alembic is a starting point for Jekyll projects. Rather than starting from scratch, this boilerplate is designed to get the ball rolling immediately</subtitle><author><name>VikrantVerma</name></author><entry><title type="html">Self Studying Linear Algebra</title><link href="https://vikv.dev/academics/2025/06/15/lin_alg_1/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Self Studying Linear Algebra" /><published>2025-06-15T00:00:00+01:00</published><updated>2025-06-15T00:00:00+01:00</updated><id>https://vikv.dev/academics/2025/06/15/lin_alg_1</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://vikv.dev/academics/2025/06/15/lin_alg_1/"><![CDATA[<p>The professor is a very engaging lecturer, although the lectures I feel are relatively short. I’m already starting to see and think about how this can applied to performing large calculations, although I’d like to look more into how these calculations can be done faster. Currently we can define an upper bound of O(n<sup>3</sup>) for matrix multiplication because we have to perform n<sup>2</sup> calculations for each row in the matrix. There are some faster algorithms like Strassen’s and Coppersmith-Winograd’s which reduce the overall time complexity to just under n<sup>3</sup>.</p>

<p>A cool improvement although the drawback of analyzing algorithms solely by their asymptotic upper bound is that we ignore constant factors which (unfortunately) do affect our real execution speed. I’d like to look more into this though!</p>]]></content><author><name>VikrantVerma</name></author><category term="Academics" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[The professor is a very engaging lecturer, although the lectures I feel are relatively short. I’m already starting to see and think about how this can applied to performing large calculations, although I’d like to look more into how these calculations can be done faster. Currently we can define an upper bound of O(n3) for matrix multiplication because we have to perform n2 calculations for each row in the matrix. There are some faster algorithms like Strassen’s and Coppersmith-Winograd’s which reduce the overall time complexity to just under n3. A cool improvement although the drawback of analyzing algorithms solely by their asymptotic upper bound is that we ignore constant factors which (unfortunately) do affect our real execution speed. I’d like to look more into this though!]]></summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="https://vikv.dev/assets/default-social-image.png" /><media:content medium="image" url="https://vikv.dev/assets/default-social-image.png" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry><title type="html">On Acting</title><link href="https://vikv.dev/general/reflections/2025/06/13/acting/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="On Acting" /><published>2025-06-13T00:00:00+01:00</published><updated>2025-06-13T00:00:00+01:00</updated><id>https://vikv.dev/general/reflections/2025/06/13/acting</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://vikv.dev/general/reflections/2025/06/13/acting/"><![CDATA[<p>Last quarter, I took an acting class. Having been reserved my entire life, this was a decision no one probably would’ve seen coming. I definitely did not anticipate my enrolling in this class.</p>

<p>When I registered, it was for two reasons:</p>
<ul>
  <li>I wanted to improve my public speaking skills</li>
  <li>I wanted to be able to finish the course early so I could start my internship</li>
</ul>

<p>In regards to the first point, I am significantly better at public speaking now than I ever was. Playing a dramatic character on stage makes doing a presentation look like nothing. As for the second point, I had to do my final performance 2-3 weeks early, which went great!</p>

<p>After I had registered for this class, my inner voice was of course telling me not to do it because I could take an ‘easier’ class that I wouldn’t have to be uncomfortable in. Sometime during the week after I signed up for the course, a spot opened up in a totally online, asynchronous course on something related to music. Logically speaking, this would’ve been much less effort. No class meeting times, and no pushing of my comfort zone. I ruminated on whether I should do it or not. I was close to registering for this class, but I ultimately didn’t.</p>

<p>Why not stay comfortable? I could always just do more presentations right? Wouldn’t the async class give me more free time to, I don’t know, study?</p>

<p>Honestly, I felt like I would’ve been running away. I knew that every reason I would come up with would be an excuse. Main takeaway? We tend to trust our own thoughts for no reason other than that they’re our own, and often times we subconsciously value relatively short-term comfort at the cost of long-term growth.</p>]]></content><author><name>VikrantVerma</name></author><category term="General" /><category term="Reflections" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Last quarter, I took an acting class. Having been reserved my entire life, this was a decision no one probably would’ve seen coming. I definitely did not anticipate my enrolling in this class. When I registered, it was for two reasons: I wanted to improve my public speaking skills I wanted to be able to finish the course early so I could start my internship In regards to the first point, I am significantly better at public speaking now than I ever was. Playing a dramatic character on stage makes doing a presentation look like nothing. As for the second point, I had to do my final performance 2-3 weeks early, which went great! After I had registered for this class, my inner voice was of course telling me not to do it because I could take an ‘easier’ class that I wouldn’t have to be uncomfortable in. Sometime during the week after I signed up for the course, a spot opened up in a totally online, asynchronous course on something related to music. Logically speaking, this would’ve been much less effort. No class meeting times, and no pushing of my comfort zone. I ruminated on whether I should do it or not. I was close to registering for this class, but I ultimately didn’t. Why not stay comfortable? I could always just do more presentations right? Wouldn’t the async class give me more free time to, I don’t know, study? Honestly, I felt like I would’ve been running away. I knew that every reason I would come up with would be an excuse. Main takeaway? We tend to trust our own thoughts for no reason other than that they’re our own, and often times we subconsciously value relatively short-term comfort at the cost of long-term growth.]]></summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="https://vikv.dev/assets/default-social-image.png" /><media:content medium="image" url="https://vikv.dev/assets/default-social-image.png" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry><title type="html">Interning at Capital One</title><link href="https://vikv.dev/career/reflections/2025/06/13/capital_one/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Interning at Capital One" /><published>2025-06-13T00:00:00+01:00</published><updated>2025-06-13T00:00:00+01:00</updated><id>https://vikv.dev/career/reflections/2025/06/13/capital_one</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://vikv.dev/career/reflections/2025/06/13/capital_one/"><![CDATA[<p>Starting week 7 of my internship here, I think I’ve learned a lot, not only in terms of how engineering works at large companies, but also about myself. This is the first time I’ve been away from home on my own for any extended period of time.</p>

<p>Some brief happenings and takeaways:</p>
<ul>
  <li>Upon arrival to the apartment, my roommate and I found that the floors were leaking.</li>
  <li>Virginia is extremely humid.
    <ul>
      <li>The bugs look weird</li>
      <li>The sky seldom looks as blue as it does Washington (state).</li>
    </ul>
  </li>
  <li>Groceries are expensive.</li>
  <li>Time moves both slower and faster.</li>
  <li>Although extremely uncomfortable, living in a new place that you don’t how to navigate rapidly expands your world view. I’ve realized Seattle and its surrounding areas are just a microcosm of what kinds of people, ideas, and things there are to experience. I’m definitely much more open to the idea of living in various other countries in the future.</li>
</ul>

<p>In terms of engineering at large companies, I’ve noticed that it’s much harder to apply the mindset of ‘just build things’ due to a variety of factors.</p>
<ul>
  <li>A certain software library may be unauthorized for use</li>
  <li>You may be waiting on approval for access to a certain API that is blocking your project</li>
  <li>Your point of contact for critical information be out of office (good for them!)</li>
</ul>

<p>The ‘bureaucracy’ has been a new experience, one that I’ve come to appreciate. More importantly, I am enjoying building things alongside a knowledgeable team, just as much as I had hoped before starting this position.</p>]]></content><author><name>VikrantVerma</name></author><category term="Career" /><category term="Reflections" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Starting week 7 of my internship here, I think I’ve learned a lot, not only in terms of how engineering works at large companies, but also about myself. This is the first time I’ve been away from home on my own for any extended period of time. Some brief happenings and takeaways: Upon arrival to the apartment, my roommate and I found that the floors were leaking. Virginia is extremely humid. The bugs look weird The sky seldom looks as blue as it does Washington (state). Groceries are expensive. Time moves both slower and faster. Although extremely uncomfortable, living in a new place that you don’t how to navigate rapidly expands your world view. I’ve realized Seattle and its surrounding areas are just a microcosm of what kinds of people, ideas, and things there are to experience. I’m definitely much more open to the idea of living in various other countries in the future. In terms of engineering at large companies, I’ve noticed that it’s much harder to apply the mindset of ‘just build things’ due to a variety of factors. A certain software library may be unauthorized for use You may be waiting on approval for access to a certain API that is blocking your project Your point of contact for critical information be out of office (good for them!) The ‘bureaucracy’ has been a new experience, one that I’ve come to appreciate. More importantly, I am enjoying building things alongside a knowledgeable team, just as much as I had hoped before starting this position.]]></summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="https://vikv.dev/assets/default-social-image.png" /><media:content medium="image" url="https://vikv.dev/assets/default-social-image.png" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry></feed>